<doc>
  <category name="German Wheat Beer" number="10">
    <paragraph>*This category contains vollbier- and starkbier-strength German wheat beers without sourness, in light and dark colors.*</paragraph>
    <style style_id="10A" style_name="Weissbier">
      <overallimpression>
        <paragraph>A pale, refreshing German wheat beer with high carbonation, dry finish, a fluffy mouthfeel, and a distinctive banana-and-clove yeast character.</paragraph>
      </overallimpression>
      <aroma>
        <paragraph>Moderate to strong phenols (usually clove) and fruity esters (typically banana). The balance and intensity of the phenol and ester components can vary but the best examples are reasonably balanced and fairly prominent. The hop character ranges from low to none. A light to moderate wheat aroma (which might be perceived as bready or grainy) may be present but other malt characteristics should not. Optional, but acceptable, aromatics can include a light to moderate vanilla character, and/or a faint bubblegum aroma. None of these optional characteristics should be high or dominant, but often can add to the complexity and balance.</paragraph>
      </aroma>
      <appearance>
        <paragraph>Pale straw to gold in color. A very thick, moussy, long-lasting white head is characteristic. The high protein content of wheat impairs clarity in an unfiltered beer, although the level of haze is somewhat variable.</paragraph>
      </appearance>
      <flavor>
        <paragraph>Low to moderately strong banana and clove flavor. The balance and intensity of the phenol and ester components can vary but the best examples are reasonably balanced and fairly prominent. Optionally, a very light to moderate vanilla character and/or faint bubblegum notes can accentuate the banana flavor, sweetness and roundness; neither should be dominant if present. The soft, somewhat bready or grainy flavor of wheat is complementary, as is a slightly grainy-sweet malt character. Hop flavor is very low to none, and hop bitterness is very low to moderately low. Well-rounded, flavorful palate with a relatively dry finish. The perception of sweetness is more due to the absence of hop bitterness than actual residual sweetness; a sweet or heavy finish would significantly impair drinkability.</paragraph>
      </flavor>
      <mouthfeel>
        <paragraph>Medium-light to medium body; never heavy. Suspended yeast may increase the perception of body. The texture of wheat imparts the sensation of a fluffy, creamy fullness that may progress to a light, spritzy finish aided by high to very high carbonation. Always effervescent.</paragraph>
      </mouthfeel>
      <comments>
        <paragraph>These are refreshing, fast-maturing beers that are lightly hopped and show a unique banana-and-clove yeast character. These beers often don't age well and are best enjoyed while young and fresh. The version *mit hefe *is served with suspended yeast; the *krystal* version is filtered for excellent clarity. The character of a krystal weizen is generally fruitier and less phenolic than that of the weissbier mit hefe. May be known as *hefeweizen*, particularly in the United States.</paragraph>
      </comments>
      <history>
        <paragraph>While Bavaria has a wheat beer tradition dating back hundreds of years, brewing wheat beer used to be a monopoly reserved for Bavarian royalty. Modern weissbier dates from 1872 when Schneider began production. However, pale weissbier only became popular since the 1960s. It is quite popular today, particularly in southern Germany.</paragraph>
      </history>
      <characteristicingredients>
        <paragraph>By German brewing tradition, at least 50% of the grist must be malted wheat, although some versions use up to 70%; the remainder is typically Pilsner malt. A decoction mash is traditional, although modern brewers typically don't follow this practice. Weizen ale yeast produces the typical spicy and fruity character, although high fermentation temperatures can affect the balance and produce off-flavors.</paragraph>
      </characteristicingredients>
      <vitalstatistics>
        <OG high="1.052" low="1.044"/>
        <FG high="1.014" low="1.010"/>
        <IBUs high="15" low="8"/>
        <SRM high="6" low="2"/>
        <ABV high="5.6" low="4.3"/>
      </vitalstatistics>
      <commercialexamples>
        <commercial_example>Ayinger Bräu Weisse</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Hacker-Pschorr Weisse</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Paulaner Hefe-Weizen Naturtrüb</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Schneider Weisse Unser Original</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Weihenstephaner Hefeweissbier</commercial_example>
      </commercialexamples>
      <tags>
        <tag>standard-strength</tag>
        <tag>pale-color</tag>
        <tag>top-fermented</tag>
        <tag>central-europe</tag>
        <tag>traditional-style</tag>
        <tag>wheat-beer-family</tag>
        <tag>malty</tag>
      </tags>
    </style>
    <style style_id="10B" style_name="Dunkles Weissbier">
      <overallimpression>
        <paragraph>A moderately dark German wheat beer with a distinctive banana-and-clove yeast character, supported by a toasted bread or caramel malt flavor. Highly carbonated and refreshing, with a creamy, fluffy texture and light finish that encourages drinking.</paragraph>
      </overallimpression>
      <aroma>
        <paragraph>Moderate phenols (usually clove) and fruity esters (usually banana). The balance and intensity of the phenol and ester components can vary but the best examples are reasonably balanced. Optionally, a low to moderate vanilla character and/or faint bubblegum notes may be present, but should not dominate. Hop aroma ranges from low to none, and may be lightly floral, spicy, or herbal. A light to moderate wheat aroma (which might be perceived as bready, doughy or grainy) may be present and is often accompanied by a caramel, bread crust, or richer malt aroma. The malt aroma may moderate the phenols and esters somewhat.</paragraph>
      </aroma>
      <appearance>
        <paragraph>Light copper to mahogany brown in color. A very thick, moussy, long-lasting off-white head is characteristic. The high protein content of wheat impairs clarity in this traditionally unfiltered style, although the level of haze is somewhat variable. Suspended yeast sediment can contribute to cloudiness.</paragraph>
      </appearance>
      <flavor>
        <paragraph>Low to moderately strong banana and clove flavor. The balance and intensity of the phenol and ester components can vary but the best examples are reasonably balanced and fairly prominent. Optionally, a very light to moderate vanilla character and/or faint bubblegum notes can accentuate the banana flavor, sweetness and roundness; neither should be dominant if present. The soft, somewhat bready, doughy, or grainy flavor of wheat is complementary, as is a richer caramel, toast, or bread crust flavor. The malty richness can be low to medium-high, and supports the yeast character. A roasted malt character is inappropriate. A spicy, herbal, or floral hop flavor is very low to none, and hop bitterness is very low to low. Well-rounded, flavorful, often somewhat malty palate with a relatively dry finish.</paragraph>
      </flavor>
      <mouthfeel>
        <paragraph>Medium-light to medium-full body. The texture of wheat as well as yeast in suspension imparts the sensation of a fluffy, creamy fullness that may progress to a lighter finish, aided by moderate to high carbonation. Effervescent.</paragraph>
      </mouthfeel>
      <comments>
        <paragraph>The presence of Munich and/or Vienna-type barley malts gives this style a deep, rich barley malt character not found in a weissbier. Often known as *dunkelweizen*, particularly in the United States.</paragraph>
      </comments>
      <history>
        <paragraph>Bavaria has a wheat beer brewing traditional hundreds of years old, but the brewing right was reserved for Bavarian royalty until the late 1700s. Old-fashioned Bavarian wheat beer was often dark, as were most beer of the day. Pale weissbier started to become popular in the 1960s, but traditional dark wheat beer remained somewhat of an old person's drink.</paragraph>
      </history>
      <characteristicingredients>
        <paragraph>By German brewing tradition, at least 50% of the grist must be malted wheat, although some versions use up to 70%; the remainder is usually Munich, Vienna, or dark or caramel wheat malts, or Pilsner malt with color malt. A decoction mash is traditional, but infrequently used today. Weizen ale yeasts produce the typical spicy and fruity character, although extreme fermentation temperatures can affect the balance and produce off-flavors.</paragraph>
      </characteristicingredients>
      <stylecomparison>
        <paragraph>Reflecting the best yeast and wheat character of a weissbier blended with the malty richness of a Munich dunkel. The banana and clove character is often less apparent than in a weissbier due to the increased maltiness.</paragraph>
      </stylecomparison>
      <vitalstatistics>
        <OG high="1.056" low="1.044"/>
        <FG high="1.014" low="1.010"/>
        <IBUs high="18" low="10"/>
        <SRM high="23" low="14"/>
        <ABV high="5.6" low="4.3"/>
      </vitalstatistics>
      <commercialexamples>
        <commercial_example>Ayinger Ur-Weisse</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Ettaler Weissbier Dunkel</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Franziskaner Hefe-Weisse Dunkel</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Hacker-Pschorr Weisse Dark</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Tucher Dunkles Hefe Weizen</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Weihenstephaner Hefeweissbier Dunkel</commercial_example>
      </commercialexamples>
      <tags>
        <tag>standard-strength</tag>
        <tag>amber-color</tag>
        <tag>top-fermented</tag>
        <tag>central-europe</tag>
        <tag>traditional-style</tag>
        <tag>wheat-beer-family</tag>
        <tag>malty</tag>
      </tags>
    </style>
    <style style_id="10C" style_name="Weizenbock">
      <overallimpression>
        <paragraph>A strong, malty, fruity, wheat-based ale combining the best malt and yeast flavors of a weissbier (pale or dark) with the malty-rich flavor, strength, and body of a Dunkles Bock or Doppelbock.</paragraph>
      </overallimpression>
      <aroma>
        <paragraph>Medium-high to high malty-rich character with a significant bready-grainy wheat component. Paler versions will have a bready-toasty malty richness, while darker versions will have a deeper, richer malt presence with significant Maillard products. The malt component is similar to a helles bock for pale versions (grainy-sweet-rich, lightly toasted) or a dunkles bock for dark versions (bready-malty-rich, highly toasted, optional caramel). The yeast contributes a typical weizen character of banana and spice (clove, vanilla), which can be medium-low to medium-high. Darker versions can have some dark fruit aroma (plums, prunes, grapes, raisins), particularly as they age. A low to moderate alcohol aroma is acceptable, but shouldn't be hot or solventy. No hop aroma. The malt, yeast, and alcohol intertwine to produce a complex, inviting, prominent bouquet.</paragraph>
      </aroma>
      <appearance>
        <paragraph>Pale and dark versions exist, with pale versions being light gold to light amber, and dark versions being dark amber to dark ruby-brown in color. A very thick, moussy, long-lasting white to off-white (pale versions) or light tan (dark versions) head is characteristic. The high protein content of wheat impairs clarity in this traditionally unfiltered style, although the level of haze is somewhat variable. Suspended yeast sediment can contribute to the cloudiness.</paragraph>
      </appearance>
      <flavor>
        <paragraph>Similar to the aroma, a medium-high to high malty-rich flavor together with a significant bready-grainy wheat flavor. Paler versions will have a bready, toasty, grainy-sweet malt richness, while darker versions will have deeper, bready-rich or toasted malt flavors with significant Maillard products, optional caramel. Low to moderate banana and spice (clove, vanilla) yeast character. Darker versions can have some dark fruit flavor (plums, prunes, grapes, raisins), particularly as they age. A light chocolate character (but not roast) is optional in darker versions. No hop flavor. A low hop bitterness can give a slightly sweet palate impression, but the beer typically finishes dry (sometimes enhanced by a light alcohol character). The interplay between the malt, yeast, and alcohol adds complexity and interest, which is often enhanced with age.</paragraph>
      </flavor>
      <mouthfeel>
        <paragraph>Medium-full to full body. A fluffy or creamy texture is typical, as is the mild warming sensation of substantial alcohol content. Moderate to high carbonation.</paragraph>
      </mouthfeel>
      <comments>
        <paragraph>A Weissbier brewed to bock or doppelbock strength. Schneider also produces an Eisbock version. Pale and dark versions exist, although dark are more common. Pale versions have less rich malt complexity and often more hops, as with doppelbocks. Lightly oxidized Maillard products can produce some rich, intense flavors and aromas that are often seen in aged imported commercial products; fresher versions will not have this character. Well-aged examples might also take on a slight sherry-like complexity.</paragraph>
      </comments>
      <history>
        <paragraph>Aventinus, the world's oldest top-fermented wheat doppelbock, was created in 1907 at the Schneider Weisse Brauhaus in Munich.</paragraph>
      </history>
      <characteristicingredients>
        <paragraph>A high percentage of malted wheat is used (by German brewing tradition must be at least 50%, although it may contain up to 70%), with the remainder being Munich- and/or Vienna-type barley malts in darker versions, and more Pils malt in paler versions. Some color malts may be used sparingly. A traditional decoction mash can give the appropriate body without cloying sweetness. Weizen ale yeasts produce the typical spicy and fruity character. Too warm or too cold fermentation will cause the phenols and esters to be out of balance and may create off-flavors. Hop choice is essentially irrelevant, but German varieties are most traditional.</paragraph>
      </characteristicingredients>
      <stylecomparison>
        <paragraph>Stronger and richer than a Weissbier or Dunkles Weissbier, but with similar yeast character. More directly comparable to the Doppelbock style, with the pale and dark variations. Can vary widely in strength, but most are in the bock to doppelbock range.</paragraph>
      </stylecomparison>
      <entryinstructions>
        <paragraph>The entrant will specify whether the entry is a **pale** or a **dark** version.</paragraph>
      </entryinstructions>
      <vitalstatistics>
        <OG high="1.090" low="1.064"/>
        <FG high="1.022" low="1.015"/>
        <IBUs high="30" low="15"/>
        <SRM high="25" low="6"/>
        <ABV high="9.0" low="6.5"/>
      </vitalstatistics>
      <commercialexamples>
        <commercial_example group="dark">Eisenbahn Weizenbock</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example group="dark">Plank Bavarian Dunkler Weizenbock</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example group="dark">Penn Weizenbock</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example group="dark">Schneider Unser Aventinus</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example group="pale">Plank Bavarian Heller Weizenbock</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example group="pale">Weihenstephaner Vitus</commercial_example>
      </commercialexamples>
      <tags>
        <tag>high-strength</tag>
        <tag>amber-color</tag>
        <tag>pale-color</tag>
        <tag>top-fermented</tag>
        <tag>central-europe</tag>
        <tag>traditional-style</tag>
        <tag>wheat-beer-family</tag>
        <tag>malty</tag>
      </tags>
    </style>
  </category>
</doc>
