<doc>
  <category name="Strong British Ale" number="17">
    <paragraph>*This category contains the stronger, non-roasty beers of the British Isles.*</paragraph>
    <style style_id="17A" style_name="British Strong Ale">
      <overallimpression>
        <paragraph>An ale of respectable alcoholic strength, traditionally bottled-conditioned and cellared. Can have a wide range of interpretations, but most will have varying degrees of malty richness, late hops and bitterness, fruity esters, and alcohol warmth. Judges should allow for a significant range in character, as long as the beer is within the alcohol strength range and has an interesting 'British' character, it likely fits the style. The malt and adjunct flavors and intensity can vary widely, but any combination should result in an agreeable palate experience.</paragraph>
      </overallimpression>
      <aroma>
        <paragraph>Malty-sweet with fruity esters, often with a complex blend of dried-fruit, caramel, nuts, toffee, and/or other specialty malt aromas. Some alcohol notes are acceptable, but shouldn't be hot or solventy. Hop aromas can vary widely, but typically have earthy, resiny, fruity, and/or floral notes. The balance can vary widely, but most examples will have a blend of malt, fruit, hops, and alcohol in varying intensities.</paragraph>
      </aroma>
      <appearance>
        <paragraph>Deep gold to dark reddish-brown color (many are fairly dark). Generally clear, although darker versions may be almost opaque. Moderate to low cream- to light tan-colored head; average retention.</paragraph>
      </appearance>
      <flavor>
        <paragraph>Medium to high malt character often rich with nutty, toffee, or caramel flavors. Light chocolate notes are sometimes found in darker beers. May have interesting flavor complexity from brewing sugars. Balance is often malty, but may be well hopped, which affects the impression of maltiness. Moderate fruity esters are common, often with a dark fruit or dried fruit character. The finish may vary from medium dry to somewhat sweet. Alcoholic strength should be evident, though not overwhelming. Diacetyl low to none, and is generally not desirable.</paragraph>
      </flavor>
      <mouthfeel>
        <paragraph>Medium to full, chewy body. Alcohol warmth is often evident and always welcome. Low to moderate carbonation. Smooth texture.</paragraph>
      </mouthfeel>
      <comments>
        <paragraph>As an entry category more than a style, the strength and character of examples can vary widely. Fits in the style space between normal gravity beers (strong bitters, brown ales, English porters) and barleywines. Can include pale malty-hoppy beers, English winter warmers, strong dark milds, smaller Burton ales, and other unique beers in the general gravity range that don't fit other categories. Traditionally a bottle-conditioned product suitable for cellaring.</paragraph>
      </comments>
      <history>
        <paragraph>The heritage varies since this category generally reflects a grouping of unrelated minor styles with limited production. Some are historical recreations while others are modern. Some directly descend from older styles such as Burton ales, while others maintain a historical connection with older beers. As a grouping, the notion is relatively modern since beers of this strength category would not have been abnormal in past centuries. Do not use this category grouping to infer historical relationships between examples; this is almost a modern British specialty category where the 'special' attribute is alcohol level.</paragraph>
      </history>
      <characteristicingredients>
        <paragraph>Grists vary, often based on pale malt with caramel and specialty malts. Some darker examples suggest that dark malts (e.g., chocolate, black malt) may be appropriate, though sparingly so as to avoid an overly roasted character. Sugary adjuncts are common, as are starchy adjuncts (maize, flaked barley, wheat). Finishing hops are traditionally English.</paragraph>
      </characteristicingredients>
      <stylecomparison>
        <paragraph>Significant overlap in gravity with old ales, but not having a stale or aged character. A wide range of interpretations is possible. Should not be as rich or strong as an English Barleywine. Stronger than the stronger everyday beers (strong bitters, brown ales, porters). More specialty malt and/or sugar character than American Strong Ales.</paragraph>
      </stylecomparison>
      <vitalstatistics>
        <OG high="1.080" low="1.055"/>
        <FG high="1.022" low="1.015"/>
        <IBUs high="60" low="30"/>
        <SRM high="22" low="8"/>
        <ABV high="8.0" low="5.5"/>
      </vitalstatistics>
      <commercialexamples>
        <commercial_example>Fuller's 1845</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Harvey's Elizabethan Ale</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>J.W. Lees Manchester Star</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Samuel Smith's Winter Welcome</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Young's Winter Warmer</commercial_example>
      </commercialexamples>
      <tags>
        <tag>high-strength</tag>
        <tag>amber-color</tag>
        <tag>top-fermented</tag>
        <tag>british-isles</tag>
        <tag>traditional-style</tag>
        <tag>strong-ale-family</tag>
        <tag>malty</tag>
      </tags>
    </style>
    <style style_id="17B" style_name="Old Ale">
      <overallimpression>
        <paragraph>An ale of moderate to fairly significant alcoholic strength, bigger than standard beers, though usually not as strong or rich as barleywine. Often tilted towards a maltier balance. "It should be a warming beer of the type that is best drunk in half pints by a warm fire on a cold winter's night" -- Michael Jackson.</paragraph>
      </overallimpression>
      <aroma>
        <paragraph>Malty-sweet with fruity esters, often with a complex blend of dried-fruit, vinous, caramelly, molasses, nutty, toffee, light treacle, and/or other specialty malt aromas. Some alcohol and oxidative notes are acceptable, akin to those found in Sherry or Port. Hop aromas not usually present due to extended aging.</paragraph>
      </aroma>
      <appearance>
        <paragraph>Light amber to very dark reddish-brown color (most are fairly dark). Age and oxidation may darken the beer further. May be almost opaque (if not, should be clear). Moderate to low cream- to light tan-colored head; may be adversely affected by alcohol and age.</paragraph>
      </appearance>
      <flavor>
        <paragraph>Medium to high malt character with a luscious malt complexity, often with nutty, caramelly and/or molasses-like flavors. Light chocolate or roasted malt flavors are optional, but should never be prominent. Balance is often malty-sweet, but may be well hopped (the impression of bitterness often depends on amount of aging). Moderate to high fruity esters are common, and may take on a dried-fruit or vinous character. The finish may vary from dry to somewhat sweet. Extended aging may contribute oxidative flavors similar to a fine old Sherry, Port or Madeira. Alcoholic strength should be evident, though not overwhelming. Diacetyl low to none. Some wood-aged or blended versions may have a lactic or Brettanomyces character; but this is optional and should not be too strong. Any acidity or tannin from age should be well-integrated and contribute to complexity in the flavor profile, not be a dominant experience.</paragraph>
      </flavor>
      <mouthfeel>
        <paragraph>Medium to full, chewy body, although older examples may be lower in body due to continued attenuation during conditioning. Alcohol warmth is often evident and always welcome. Low to moderate carbonation, depending on age and conditioning. Light acidity may be present, as well as some tannin if wood-aged; both are optional.</paragraph>
      </mouthfeel>
      <comments>
        <paragraph>Strength and character varies widely. The predominant defining quality for this style is the impression of age, which can manifest itself in different ways (complexity, lactic, Brett, oxidation, leather, vinous qualities, etc.). Even if these qualities are otherwise faults, if the resulting character of the beer is still pleasantly drinkable and complex, then those characteristics are acceptable. In no way should those allowable characteristics be interpreted as making an undrinkably off beer as somehow in style. Old Peculier is a fairly unique type of beer that is quite different than other Old Ales.</paragraph>
      </comments>
      <history>
        <paragraph>Historically, an aged ale used as stock ales for blending or enjoyed at full strength (stale or stock refers to beers that were aged or stored for a significant period of time). There are at least two definite types in Britain today, weaker draught ones that are similar aged milds of around 4.5%, and stronger ones that are often 6-8% or more.</paragraph>
      </history>
      <characteristicingredients>
        <paragraph>Composition varies, although generally similar to British Strong Ales. The age character is the biggest driver of the final style profile, which is more handling than brewing. May be aged in wood, but should not have a strong wood character.</paragraph>
      </characteristicingredients>
      <stylecomparison>
        <paragraph>Roughly overlapping the British Strong Ale and the lower end of the English Barleywine styles, but always having an aged quality. The distinction between an Old Ale and a Barleywine is somewhat arbitrary above 7% ABV, and generally means having a more significant aged quality (particularly from wood). Barleywines tend to develop more of a 'mature' quality, while Old Ales can show more of the barrel qualities (lactic, Brett, vinous, etc.).</paragraph>
      </stylecomparison>
      <vitalstatistics>
        <OG high="1.088" low="1.055"/>
        <FG high="1.022" low="1.015"/>
        <IBUs high="60" low="30"/>
        <SRM high="22" low="10"/>
        <ABV high="9.0" low="5.5"/>
      </vitalstatistics>
      <commercialexamples>
        <commercial_example>Burton Bridge Olde Expensive</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Gale's Prize Old Ale</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Greene King Strong Suffolk Ale</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Marston Owd Roger</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Theakston Old Peculier</commercial_example>
      </commercialexamples>
      <tags>
        <tag>high-strength</tag>
        <tag>amber-color</tag>
        <tag>top-fermented</tag>
        <tag>british-isles</tag>
        <tag>traditional-style</tag>
        <tag>strong-ale-family</tag>
        <tag>malty</tag>
        <tag>aged</tag>
      </tags>
    </style>
    <style style_id="17C" style_name="Wee Heavy">
      <overallimpression>
        <paragraph>Rich, malty, dextrinous, and usually caramel-sweet, these beers can give an impression that is suggestive of a dessert. Complex secondary malt and alcohol flavors prevent a one-dimensional quality. Strength and maltiness can vary, but should not be cloying or syrupy.</paragraph>
      </overallimpression>
      <aroma>
        <paragraph>Deeply malty, with a strong caramel component. Lightly smoky secondary aromas may also be present, adding complexity; peat smoke is inappropriate. Diacetyl should be low to none. Low to moderate esters and alcohol are often present in stronger versions. Hops are very low to none, and can be slightly earthy or floral.</paragraph>
      </aroma>
      <appearance>
        <paragraph>Light copper to dark brown color, often with deep ruby highlights. Clear. Usually has a large tan head, which may not persist. Legs may be evident in stronger versions.</paragraph>
      </appearance>
      <flavor>
        <paragraph>Richly malty with significant caramel (particularly in stronger versions). Hints of roasted malt may be present (sometimes perceived as a faint smoke character), as may some nutty character, all of which may last into the finish. Peat smoke is inappropriate. Hop flavors and bitterness are low to medium-low, so the malt presence should dominate the balance. Diacetyl should be low to none. Low to moderate esters and alcohol are usually present. Esters may suggest plums, raisins or dried fruit. The palate is usually full and sweet, but the finish may be sweet to medium-dry, sometimes with a light roasty-grainy note.</paragraph>
      </flavor>
      <mouthfeel>
        <paragraph>Medium-full to full-bodied, with some versions (but not all) having a thick, chewy viscosity. A smooth, alcoholic warmth is usually present and is quite welcome since it balances the malty sweetness. Moderate carbonation.</paragraph>
      </mouthfeel>
      <comments>
        <paragraph>Also known as "strong Scotch ale." The term "wee heavy" means "small strong" and traces to the beer that made the term famous, Fowler's Wee Heavy, a 12 Guinea Ale. Historically, the strongest beer from a Scottish ale parti-gyle.</paragraph>
      </comments>
      <history>
        <paragraph>More related to historical brews than modern lower-strength Scottish ales, these beers have their roots in the strong ales of the 1700s and 1800s, although formulations and methods have changed. A premium product, often produced for export. Modern versions have lower starting and finishing gravities than their historical ancestors.</paragraph>
      </history>
      <characteristicingredients>
        <paragraph>Well-modified pale malt, with roasted barley for color. May use some crystal malt for color adjustment. Slight smoke character may be present in some versions, but derives from roasted grains or from the boil. Peated malt is absolutely not traditional.</paragraph>
      </characteristicingredients>
      <stylecomparison>
        <paragraph>Somewhat similar to an English Barleywine.</paragraph>
      </stylecomparison>
      <vitalstatistics>
        <OG high="1.130" low="1.070"/>
        <FG high="1.040" low="1.018"/>
        <IBUs high="35" low="17"/>
        <SRM high="25" low="14"/>
        <ABV high="10.0" low="6.5"/>
      </vitalstatistics>
      <commercialexamples>
        <commercial_example>Belhaven Wee Heavy</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Gordon Highland Scotch Ale</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Inveralmond Blackfriar</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>McEwan's Scotch Ale</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Orkney Skull Splitter</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Traquair House Ale</commercial_example>
      </commercialexamples>
      <tags>
        <tag>high-strength</tag>
        <tag>amber-color</tag>
        <tag>top-fermented</tag>
        <tag>british-isles</tag>
        <tag>traditional-style</tag>
        <tag>strong-ale-family</tag>
        <tag>malty</tag>
      </tags>
    </style>
    <style style_id="17D" style_name="English Barleywine">
      <overallimpression>
        <paragraph>A showcase of malty richness and complex, intense flavors. Chewy and rich in body, with warming alcohol and a pleasant fruity or hoppy interest. When aged, it can take on port-like flavors. A wintertime sipper.</paragraph>
      </overallimpression>
      <aroma>
        <paragraph>Very rich and strongly malty, often with a caramel-like aroma in darker versions or a light toffee character in paler versions. May have moderate to strong fruitiness, often with a dark- or dried-fruit character, particularly in dark versions. The hop aroma may range from mild to assertive, and is typically floral, earthy, or marmalade-like. Alcohol aromatics may be low to moderate, but are soft and rounded. The intensity of these aromatics often subsides with age. The aroma may have a rich character including bready, toasty, toffee, and/or molasses notes. Aged versions may have a sherry-like quality, possibly vinous or port-like aromatics, and generally more muted malt aromas.</paragraph>
      </aroma>
      <appearance>
        <paragraph>Color may range from rich gold to very dark amber or even dark brown (often has ruby highlights, but should not be opaque). Low to moderate off-white head; may have low head retention. May be cloudy with chill haze at cooler temperatures, but generally clears to good to brilliant clarity as it warms. The color may appear to have great depth, as if viewed through a thick glass lens. High alcohol and viscosity may be visible in "legs" when beer is swirled in a glass.</paragraph>
      </appearance>
      <flavor>
        <paragraph>Strong, intense, complex, multi-layered malt flavors ranging from bready, toffee, and biscuity in paler versions through nutty, deep toast, dark caramel, and/or molasses in darker versions. Moderate to high malty sweetness on the palate, although the finish may be moderately sweet to moderately dry (depending on aging). Some oxidative or vinous flavors may be present, and often complex alcohol flavors should be evident. Moderate to fairly high fruitiness, often with a dark- or dried-fruit character. Hop bitterness may range from just enough for balance to a firm presence; balance therefore ranges from malty to somewhat bitter. Pale versions are often more bitter, better attenuated, and might show more hop character than darker versions; however, all versions are malty in the balance. Low to moderately high hop flavor, often floral, earthy, or marmalade-like English varieties.</paragraph>
      </flavor>
      <mouthfeel>
        <paragraph>Full-bodied and chewy, with a velvety, luscious texture (although the body may decline with long conditioning). A smooth warmth from aged alcohol should be present. Carbonation may be low to moderate, depending on age and conditioning.</paragraph>
      </mouthfeel>
      <comments>
        <paragraph>The richest and strongest of modern English Ales. The character of these ales can change significantly over time; both young and old versions should be appreciated for what they are. The malt profile can vary widely; not all examples will have all possible flavors or aromas. Paler varieties won't have the caramel and richer malt flavors, nor will they typically have the darker dried fruits -- don't expect flavors and aromatics that are impossible from a beer of that color. Typically written as "Barley Wine" in the UK, and "Barleywine" in the US.</paragraph>
      </comments>
      <history>
        <paragraph>Strong ales of various formulations have long been brewed in England, and were known by several names. The modern barleywine traces back to Bass No. 1, which was first called a barleywine in 1872. Barleywines were darker beers until Tennant (now Whitbread) first produced Gold Label, a gold-colored barleywine in 1951. Usually the strongest ale offered by a brewery, and in recent years many commercial examples are now vintage-dated and offered as a limited-release winter seasonal specialty. The original barleywine style that inspired derivative variations in Belgium, the United States, and elsewhere in the world.</paragraph>
      </history>
      <characteristicingredients>
        <paragraph>High-quality, well-modified pale malt should form the backbone of the grist, with judicious amounts of caramel malts. Dark malts should be used with great restraint, if at all, as most of the color arises from a lengthy boil. English hops such as Northdown, Target, East Kent Goldings and Fuggles are typical. Characterful British yeast.</paragraph>
      </characteristicingredients>
      <stylecomparison>
        <paragraph>Although often a hoppy beer, the English Barleywine places less emphasis on hop character than the American Barleywine and features English hops. English versions can be darker, maltier, fruitier, and feature richer specialty malt flavors than American Barleywines. Has some overlap British Old Ale on the lower end, but generally does not have the vinous qualities of age; rather, it tends to display the mature, elegant signs of age.</paragraph>
      </stylecomparison>
      <vitalstatistics>
        <OG high="1.120" low="1.080"/>
        <FG high="1.030" low="1.018"/>
        <IBUs high="70" low="35"/>
        <SRM high="22" low="8"/>
        <ABV high="12.0" low="8.0"/>
      </vitalstatistics>
      <commercialexamples>
        <commercial_example>Adnams Tally-Ho</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Burton Bridge Thomas Sykes Old Ale</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Coniston No. 9 Barley Wine</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Fuller's Golden Pride</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>J.W. Lee's Vintage Harvest Ale</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Robinson's Old Tom</commercial_example>
      </commercialexamples>
      <tags>
        <tag>very-high-strength</tag>
        <tag>amber-color</tag>
        <tag>top-fermented</tag>
        <tag>british-isles</tag>
        <tag>traditional-style</tag>
        <tag>strong-ale-family</tag>
        <tag>malty</tag>
      </tags>
    </style>
  </category>
</doc>
