<doc>
  <category name="Amber and Brown American Beer" number="19">
    <paragraph>*This category contains modern American amber and brown warm-fermented beers of standard strength that can be balanced to bitter.*</paragraph>
    <style style_id="19A" style_name="American Amber Ale">
      <overallimpression>
        <paragraph>An amber, hoppy, moderate-strength American craft beer with a caramel malty flavor. The balance can vary quite a bit, with some versions being fairly malty and others being aggressively hoppy. Hoppy and bitter versions should not have clashing flavors with the caramel malt profile.</paragraph>
      </overallimpression>
      <aroma>
        <paragraph>Low to moderate hop aroma with characteristics typical of American or New World hop varieties (citrus, floral, pine, resinous, spicy, tropical fruit, stone fruit, berry, or melon). A citrusy hop character is common, but not required. Moderately-low to moderately-high maltiness (usually with a moderate caramel character), which can either support, balance, or sometimes mask the hop presentation. Esters vary from moderate to none.</paragraph>
      </aroma>
      <appearance>
        <paragraph>Amber to coppery-brown in color. Moderately large off-white head with good retention. Generally quite clear, although dry-hopped versions may be slightly hazy.</paragraph>
      </appearance>
      <flavor>
        <paragraph>Moderate to high hop flavor with characteristics typical of American or New World hop varieties (citrus, floral, pine, resinous, spicy, tropical fruit, stone fruit, berry, or melon). A citrusy hop character is common, but not required. Malt flavors are moderate to strong, and usually show an initial malty sweetness followed by a moderate caramel flavor (and sometimes other character malts in lesser amounts). Malt and hop bitterness are usually balanced and mutually supportive, but can vary either way. Fruity esters can be moderate to none. Caramel sweetness and hop flavor/bitterness can linger somewhat into the medium to full finish.</paragraph>
      </flavor>
      <mouthfeel>
        <paragraph>Medium to medium-full body. Medium to high carbonation. Overall smooth finish without astringency. Stronger versions may have a slight alcohol warmth.</paragraph>
      </mouthfeel>
      <comments>
        <paragraph>Can overlap in color with darker American pale ales, but with a different malt flavor and balance. Regional variations exist with some being fairly mainstream and others being quite aggressive in hopping. Stronger and more bitter versions are now split into the *Red IPA *style.</paragraph>
      </comments>
      <history>
        <paragraph>A modern American craft beer style developed as a variation from American Pale Ales. Known simply as Red Ales in some regions, these beers were popularized in the hop-loving Northern California and the Pacific Northwest areas before spreading nationwide.</paragraph>
      </history>
      <characteristicingredients>
        <paragraph>Pale ale malt, typically North American two-row. Medium to dark crystal malts. May also contain specialty grains which add additional character and uniqueness. American or New World hops, often with citrusy flavors, are common but others may also be used.</paragraph>
      </characteristicingredients>
      <stylecomparison>
        <paragraph>Darker, more caramelly, more body, and generally less bitter in the balance than American Pale Ales. Less alcohol, bitterness, and hop character than Red IPAs. Less strength, malt, and hop character than American Strong Ales. Should not have a strong chocolate or roast character that might suggest an American brown ale (although small amounts are OK).</paragraph>
      </stylecomparison>
      <vitalstatistics>
        <OG high="1.060" low="1.045"/>
        <FG high="1.015" low="1.010"/>
        <IBUs high="40" low="25"/>
        <SRM high="17" low="10"/>
        <ABV high="6.2" low="4.5"/>
      </vitalstatistics>
      <commercialexamples>
        <commercial_example>Deschutes Cinder Cone Red</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Full Sail Amber</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Kona Lavaman Red Ale</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>North Coast Ruedrich's Red Seal Ale</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Rogue American Amber Ale</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Tröegs HopBack Amber Ale</commercial_example>
      </commercialexamples>
      <tags>
        <tag>standard-strength</tag>
        <tag>amber-color</tag>
        <tag>top-fermented</tag>
        <tag>north-america</tag>
        <tag>craft-style</tag>
        <tag>amber-ale-family</tag>
        <tag>balanced</tag>
        <tag>hoppy</tag>
      </tags>
    </style>
    <style style_id="19B" style_name="California Common">
      <overallimpression>
        <paragraph>A lightly fruity beer with firm, grainy maltiness, interesting toasty and caramel flavors, and showcasing rustic, traditional American hop characteristics.</paragraph>
      </overallimpression>
      <aroma>
        <paragraph>Typically showcases rustic, traditional American hops (often with woody, rustic or minty qualities) in moderate to high strength. Light fruitiness acceptable. Low to moderate caramel and/or toasty malt aromatics support the hops.</paragraph>
      </aroma>
      <appearance>
        <paragraph>Medium amber to light copper color. Generally clear. Moderate off-white head with good retention.</paragraph>
      </appearance>
      <flavor>
        <paragraph>Moderately malty with a pronounced hop bitterness. The malt character is usually toasty (not roasted) and caramelly. Low to moderately high hop flavor, usually showing rustic, traditional American hop qualities (often woody, rustic, minty). Finish fairly dry and crisp, with a lingering hop bitterness and a firm, grainy malt flavor. Light fruity esters are acceptable, but otherwise clean.</paragraph>
      </flavor>
      <mouthfeel>
        <paragraph>Medium-bodied. Medium to medium-high carbonation.</paragraph>
      </mouthfeel>
      <comments>
        <paragraph>This style is narrowly defined around the prototypical Anchor Steam example, although allowing other typical ingredients of the era. Northern Brewer hops are not a strict requirement for the style; modern American and New World-type hops (especially citrusy ones) are inappropriate, however.</paragraph>
      </comments>
      <history>
        <paragraph>American West Coast original, brewed originally as Steam Beer in the Gold Rush era. Large shallow open fermenters (coolships) were traditionally used to compensate for the absence of refrigeration and to take advantage of the cool ambient temperatures in the San Francisco Bay area. Fermented with a lager yeast, but one that was selected to ferment relatively clean beer at warmer temperatures. Modern versions are based on Anchor Brewing re-launching the style in the 1970s.</paragraph>
      </history>
      <characteristicingredients>
        <paragraph>Pale ale malt, non-citrusy hops (often Northern Brewer), small amounts of toasted malt and/or crystal malts. Lager yeast; however, some strains (often with the mention of "California" in the name) work better than others at the warmer fermentation temperatures (55 to 60 °F) typically used. Note that some German yeast strains produce inappropriate sulfury character.</paragraph>
      </characteristicingredients>
      <stylecomparison>
        <paragraph>Superficially similar to an American Amber Ale, but with specific choices for malt and hopping -- the hop flavor/aroma is traditional (not modern) American hops, malt flavors are more toasty, the hopping is always assertive, and a warm-fermented lager yeast is used. Less attenuated, less carbonated and less fruity than Australian Sparkling ale.</paragraph>
      </stylecomparison>
      <vitalstatistics>
        <OG high="1.054" low="1.048"/>
        <FG high="1.014" low="1.011"/>
        <IBUs high="45" low="30"/>
        <SRM high="14" low="10"/>
        <ABV high="5.5" low="4.5"/>
      </vitalstatistics>
      <commercialexamples>
        <commercial_example>Anchor Steam</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Flying Dog Old Scratch Amber Lager</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Schlafly Pi Common</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Steamworks Steam Engine Lager</commercial_example>
      </commercialexamples>
      <tags>
        <tag>standard-strength</tag>
        <tag>amber-color</tag>
        <tag>bottom-fermented</tag>
        <tag>north-america</tag>
        <tag>traditional-style</tag>
        <tag>amber-lager-family</tag>
        <tag>bitter</tag>
        <tag>hoppy</tag>
      </tags>
    </style>
    <style style_id="19C" style_name="American Brown Ale">
      <overallimpression>
        <paragraph>A malty but hoppy beer frequently with chocolate and caramel flavors. The hop flavor and aroma complements and enhances the malt rather than clashing with it.</paragraph>
      </overallimpression>
      <aroma>
        <paragraph>Moderate malty-sweet to malty-rich aroma with chocolate, caramel, nutty, and/or toasty qualities. Hop aroma is typically low to moderate, of almost any variety that complements the malt. Some interpretations of the style may feature a stronger hop aroma, an American or New World hop character (citrusy, fruity, tropical, etc.), and/or a fresh dry-hopped aroma (all are optional). Fruity esters are moderate to very low. The dark malt character is more robust than other brown ales, yet stops short of being overly porter-like. The malt and hops are generally balanced.</paragraph>
      </aroma>
      <appearance>
        <paragraph>Light to very dark brown color. Clear. Low to moderate off-white to light tan head.</paragraph>
      </appearance>
      <flavor>
        <paragraph>Medium to moderately-high malty-sweet or malty-rich flavor with chocolate, caramel, nutty, and/or toasty malt complexity, with medium to medium-high bitterness. The medium to medium-dry finish provides an aftertaste having both malt and hops. Hop flavor can be light to moderate, and may optionally have a citrusy, fruity, or tropical character, although any hop flavor that complements the malt is acceptable. Very low to moderate fruity esters.</paragraph>
      </flavor>
      <mouthfeel>
        <paragraph>Medium to medium-full body. More bitter versions may have a dry, resiny impression. Moderate to moderately-high carbonation.</paragraph>
      </mouthfeel>
      <comments>
        <paragraph>Most commercial American Browns are not as aggressive as the original homebrewed versions, and some modern craft-brewed examples. This style reflects the current commercial offerings typically marketed as American Brown Ales rather than the hoppier, stronger homebrew versions from the early days of homebrewing. These IPA-strength brown ales should be entered in the *Specialty IPA *as Brown IPAs.</paragraph>
      </comments>
      <history>
        <paragraph>An American style from the modern craft beer era. Derived from English Brown Ales, but with more hops. Pete's Wicked Ale was one of the first and best known examples, and inspired many imitations. Popular with homebrewers, where very hoppy versions were sometimes called *Texas Brown Ales* (this is now more appropriately a Brown IPA).</paragraph>
      </history>
      <characteristicingredients>
        <paragraph>Well-modified pale malt, plus crystal and darker malts (typically chocolate). American hops are typical, but continental or New World hops can also be used.</paragraph>
      </characteristicingredients>
      <stylecomparison>
        <paragraph>More chocolate and caramel type flavors than American Pale or Amber Ales, typically with less prominent bitterness in the balance. Less bitterness, alcohol, and hop character than Brown IPAs. More bitter and generally hoppier than English Brown Ales, with a richer malt presence, usually higher alcohol, and American/New World hop character.</paragraph>
      </stylecomparison>
      <vitalstatistics>
        <OG high="1.060" low="1.045"/>
        <FG high="1.016" low="1.010"/>
        <IBUs high="30" low="20"/>
        <SRM high="35" low="18"/>
        <ABV high="6.2" low="4.3"/>
      </vitalstatistics>
      <commercialexamples>
        <commercial_example>Anchor Brekle's Brown</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Big Sky Moose Drool Brown Ale</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Brooklyn Brown Ale</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Bell's Best Brown</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Cigar City Maduro Brown Ale</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Smuttynose Old Brown Dog Ale</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Telluride Face Down Brown</commercial_example>
      </commercialexamples>
      <tags>
        <tag>standard-strength</tag>
        <tag>dark-color</tag>
        <tag>top-fermented</tag>
        <tag>north-america</tag>
        <tag>craft-style</tag>
        <tag>brown-ale-family</tag>
        <tag>balanced</tag>
        <tag>hoppy</tag>
      </tags>
    </style>
  </category>
</doc>
