<doc>
  <category name="Strong Belgian Ale" number="25">
    <paragraph>*This category contains the pale, well-attenuated, balanced to bitter beers, often more driven by yeast character than malt flavors, with generally higher alcohol (although a range exists within styles).*</paragraph>
    <style style_id="25A" style_name="Belgian Blond Ale">
      <overallimpression>
        <paragraph>A moderate-strength golden ale that has a subtle fruity-spicy Belgian yeast complexity, slightly malty-sweet flavor, and dry finish.</paragraph>
      </overallimpression>
      <aroma>
        <paragraph>Light earthy or spicy hop nose, along with a lightly grainy-sweet malt character. Shows a subtle yeast character that may include spicy phenolics, perfumy or honey-like alcohol, or yeasty, fruity esters (commonly orange-like or lemony). Light sweetness that may have a slightly sugar-like character. Subtle yet complex.</paragraph>
      </aroma>
      <appearance>
        <paragraph>Light to deep gold color. Generally very clear. Large, dense, and creamy white to off-white head. Good head retention with Belgian lace.</paragraph>
      </appearance>
      <flavor>
        <paragraph>Smooth, light to moderate grainy-sweet malt flavor initially, but finishes medium-dry to dry with some smooth alcohol becoming evident in the aftertaste. Medium hop and alcohol bitterness to balance. Light hop flavor, can be spicy or earthy. Very soft yeast character (esters and alcohols, which are sometimes perfumy or orange/lemon-like). Light spicy phenolics optional. Some lightly caramelized sugar or honey-like sweetness on palate.</paragraph>
      </flavor>
      <mouthfeel>
        <paragraph>Medium-high to high carbonation, can give mouth-filling bubbly sensation. Medium body. Light to moderate alcohol warmth, but smooth. Can be somewhat creamy.</paragraph>
      </mouthfeel>
      <comments>
        <paragraph>Often has an almost lager-like character, which gives it a cleaner profile in comparison to many other Belgian styles. Belgians use the term *Blond*, while the French spell it *Blonde*. Most commercial examples are in the 6.5 - 7% ABV range. Many Trappist or artisanal Belgian beers are called *Blond* but those are not representative of this style.</paragraph>
      </comments>
      <history>
        <paragraph>Relatively recent development to further appeal to European Pils drinkers, becoming more popular as it is heavily marketed and widely distributed.</paragraph>
      </history>
      <characteristicingredients>
        <paragraph>Belgian Pils malt, aromatic malts, sugar, Belgian yeast strains that produce complex alcohol, phenolics and perfumy esters, Saazer-type, Styrian Goldings, or East Kent Goldings hops. Spices are not traditionally used, although the ingredients and fermentation by-products may give an impression of spicing (often reminiscent of oranges or lemons). If spices are present, should be a background character only.</paragraph>
      </characteristicingredients>
      <stylecomparison>
        <paragraph>Similar strength as a Dubbel, similar character as a Belgian Strong Golden Ale or Tripel, although a bit sweeter and not as bitter.</paragraph>
      </stylecomparison>
      <vitalstatistics>
        <OG high="1.075" low="1.062"/>
        <FG high="1.018" low="1.008"/>
        <IBUs high="30" low="15"/>
        <SRM high="7" low="4"/>
        <ABV high="7.5" low="6.0"/>
      </vitalstatistics>
      <commercialexamples>
        <commercial_example>Affligem Blond</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Grimbergen Blond</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>La Trappe Blond</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Leffe Blond</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Val-Dieu Blond</commercial_example>
      </commercialexamples>
      <tags>
        <tag>high-strength</tag>
        <tag>pale-color</tag>
        <tag>top-fermented</tag>
        <tag>western-europe</tag>
        <tag>traditional-style</tag>
        <tag>balanced</tag>
      </tags>
    </style>
    <style style_id="25B" style_name="Saison">
      <overallimpression>
        <paragraph>Most commonly, a pale, refreshing, highly-attenuated, moderately-bitter, moderate-strength Belgian ale with a very dry finish. Typically highly carbonated, and using non-barley cereal grains and optional spices for complexity, as complements the expressive yeast character that is fruity, spicy, and not overly phenolic. Less common variations include both lower-alcohol and higher-alcohol products, as well as darker versions with additional malt character.</paragraph>
      </overallimpression>
      <aroma>
        <paragraph>Quite aromatic, with fruity, spicy, and hoppy characteristics evident. The esters can be fairly high (moderate to high), and are often reminiscent of citrus fruits such as oranges or lemons. The hops are low to moderate and are often spicy, floral, earthy, or fruity. Stronger versions can have a soft, spicy alcohol note (low intensity). Spicy notes are typically peppery rather than clove-like, and can be up to moderately-strong (typically yeast-derived). Subtle, complementary herb or spice additions are allowable, but should not dominate. The malt character is typically slightly grainy in character and low in intensity. Darker and stronger versions will have more noticeable malt, with darker versions taking characteristics associated with grains of that color (toasty, biscuity, caramelly, chocolate, etc.). In versions where sourness is present instead of bitterness, some of the sour character can be detected (low to moderate).</paragraph>
      </aroma>
      <appearance>
        <paragraph>Pale versions are often a distinctive pale orange but may be pale golden to amber in color (gold to amber-gold is most common). Darker versions may run from copper to dark brown. Long-lasting, dense, rocky white to ivory head resulting in characteristic Belgian lace on the glass as it fades. Clarity is poor to good, though haze is not unexpected in this type of unfiltered beer. Effervescent.</paragraph>
      </appearance>
      <flavor>
        <paragraph>Medium-low to medium-high fruity and spicy flavors, supported by a low to medium soft malt character, often with some grainy flavors. Bitterness is typically moderate to high, although sourness can be present in place of bitterness (both should not be strong flavors at the same time). Attenuation is extremely high, which gives a characteristic dry finish essential to the style; a Saison should never finish sweet. The fruity character is frequently citrusy (orange or lemon), and the spices are typically peppery. Allow for a range of balance in the fruity-spicy characteristics; this is often driven by the yeast selection. Hop flavor is low to moderate, and generally spicy or earthy in character. The balance is towards the fruity, spicy, hoppy character, with any bitterness or sourness not overwhelming these flavors. Darker versions will have more malt character, with a range of flavors derived from darker malts (toasty, bready, biscuity, chocolate, etc.) that support the fruity-spicy character of the beer (roasted flavors are not typical). Stronger versions will have more malt flavor in general, as well as a light alcohol impression. Herbs and spices are completely optional, but if present should be used in moderation and not detract from the yeast character. The finish is very dry and the aftertaste is typically bitter and spicy. The hop bitterness can be restrained, although it can seem accentuated due to the high attenuation levels.</paragraph>
      </flavor>
      <mouthfeel>
        <paragraph>Light to medium body. Alcohol sensation varies with strength, from none in table version to light in standard versions, to moderate in super versions. However, any warming character should be fairly low. Very high carbonation with an effervescent quality. There is enough prickly acidity on the tongue to balance the very dry finish. In versions with sourness, a low to moderate tart character can add a refreshing bite, but not be puckering (optional).</paragraph>
      </mouthfeel>
      <comments>
        <paragraph>Variations exist in strength and color, but they all have similar characteristics and balance, in particularly the refreshing, highly-attenuated, dry character with high carbonation. There is no correlation between strength and color. The balance can change somewhat with strength and color variations, but the family resemblance to the original artisanal ale should be evident. Pale versions are likely to be more bitter and have more hop character, while darker versions tend to have more malt character and sweetness, yielding a more balanced presentations. Stronger versions often will have more malt flavor, richness, and body simply due to their higher gravity. Although they tend to be very well-attenuated, they may not be perceived to be as dry as standard-strength saisons due to their strength. The Saison yeast character is a must, although maltier and richer versions will tend to mask this character more. Often called *Farmhouse ales* in the US, but this term is not common in Europe where they are simply part of a larger grouping of *artisanal ales*.</paragraph>
      </comments>
      <history>
        <paragraph>A provision ale originally brewed in Wallonia, the French-speaking part of Belgium, for consumption during the active farming season. Originally a lower-alcohol product so as to not debilitate field workers, but tavern-strength products also existed. Higher-strength and different-colored products appeared after WWII. The best known modern saison, Saison Dupont, was first produced in the 1920s. Originally a rustic, artisanal ale made with local farm-produced ingredients, it is now brewed mostly in larger breweries yet retains the image of its humble origins.</paragraph>
      </history>
      <characteristicingredients>
        <paragraph>Not typically spiced, with the yeast, hops and grain providing the character; but spices are allowed if they provide a complementary character. Continental base malts are typical, but the grist frequently contains other grains such as wheat, oats, rye, or spelt. Adjuncts such as sugar and honey can also serve to add complexity and dry out the beer. Darker versions will typically use richer, darker malts, but not typically roasted types. Saazer-type, Styrian or East Kent Golding hops are commonly used. A wide range of herbs or spices can add complexity and uniqueness, but should always meld well with the yeast and hop character. Brettanomyces is not typical for this style; Saisons with Brett should be entered in the *American Wild Ale *category.</paragraph>
      </characteristicingredients>
      <stylecomparison>
        <paragraph>At standard strengths and pale color (the most common variety), like a more highly-attenuated, hoppy, and bitter Belgian blond ale with a stronger yeast character. At super strength and pale color, similar to a Belgian tripel, but often with more of a grainy, rustic quality and sometimes with a spicier yeast character.</paragraph>
      </stylecomparison>
      <entryinstructions>
        <paragraph>The entrant **must** specify the *strength* (table, standard, super) and the *color* (pale, dark).</paragraph>
      </entryinstructions>
      <vitalstatistics>
        <OG high="1.065" low="1.048">*(standard)*</OG>
        <FG high="1.008" low="1.002">*(standard)*</FG>
        <IBUs high="35" low="20"/>
        <SRM high="14" low="5">*(pale)*</SRM>
        <SRM high="22" low="15">*(dark)*</SRM>
        <ABV high="5.0" low="3.5">*(table)*</ABV>
        <ABV high="7.0" low="5.0">*(standard)*</ABV>
        <ABV high="9.5" low="7.0">*(super)*</ABV>
      </vitalstatistics>
      <commercialexamples>
        <commercial_example>Ellezelloise Saison</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Fantôme Saison</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Lefebvre Saison 1900</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Saison Dupont Vieille Provision</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Saison de Pipaix</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Saison Regal</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Saison Voisin</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Boulevard Tank 7 Farmhouse Ale</commercial_example>
      </commercialexamples>
      <tags>
        <tag>standard-strength</tag>
        <tag>pale-color</tag>
        <tag>top-fermented</tag>
        <tag>western-europe</tag>
        <tag>traditional-style</tag>
        <tag>bitter</tag>
      </tags>
    </style>
    <style style_id="25C" style_name="Belgian Golden Strong Ale">
      <overallimpression>
        <paragraph>A pale, complex, effervescent, strong Belgian-style ale that is highly attenuated and features fruity and hoppy notes in preference to phenolics.</paragraph>
      </overallimpression>
      <aroma>
        <paragraph>Complex with significant fruity esters, moderate spiciness and low to moderate alcohol and hop aromas. Esters are reminiscent of lighter fruits such as pears, oranges or apples. Moderate to moderately low spicy, peppery phenols. A low to moderate yet distinctive perfumy, floral hop character is often present. Alcohols are soft, spicy, perfumy and low-to-moderate in intensity. No hot alcohol or solventy aromas. The malt character is light and slightly grainy-sweet to nearly neutral.</paragraph>
      </aroma>
      <appearance>
        <paragraph>Yellow to medium gold in color. Good clarity. Effervescent. Massive, long-lasting, rocky, often beady, white head resulting in characteristic Belgian lace on the glass as it fades.</paragraph>
      </appearance>
      <flavor>
        <paragraph>Marriage of fruity, spicy and alcohol flavors supported by a soft malt character. Esters are reminiscent of pears, oranges or apples. Low to moderately low phenols are peppery in character. A low to moderate spicy hop character is often present. Alcohols are soft and spicy, and are low-to-moderate in intensity. Bitterness is typically medium to high from a combination of hop bitterness and yeast-produced phenolics. Substantial carbonation and bitterness leads to a dry finish with a low to moderately bitter aftertaste.</paragraph>
      </flavor>
      <mouthfeel>
        <paragraph>Very highly carbonated; effervescent. Light to medium body, although lighter than the substantial gravity would suggest. Smooth but noticeable alcohol warmth. No hot alcohol or solventy character.</paragraph>
      </mouthfeel>
      <comments>
        <paragraph>References to the devil are included in the names of many commercial examples of this style, referring to their potent alcoholic strength and as a tribute to the original example (Duvel). The best examples are complex and delicate. High carbonation helps to bring out the many flavors and to increase the perception of a dry finish. Traditionally bottle-conditioned (or *refermented in the bottle*).</paragraph>
      </comments>
      <history>
        <paragraph>Originally developed by the Moortgat brewery after WWI as a response to the growing popularity of Pilsner beers.</paragraph>
      </history>
      <characteristicingredients>
        <paragraph>Pilsner malt with substantial sugary adjuncts. Saazer-type hops or Styrian Goldings are commonly used. Belgian yeast strains are used -- those that produce fruity esters, spicy phenolics and higher alcohols -- often aided by slightly warmer fermentation temperatures. Fairly soft water. Spicing is not traditional; if present, should be a background character only.</paragraph>
      </characteristicingredients>
      <stylecomparison>
        <paragraph>Strongly resembles a Tripel, but may be even paler, lighter-bodied and even crisper and drier; the drier finish and lighter body also serves to make the assertive hopping and yeast character more prominent. Tends to use yeast that favor ester development (particularly pome fruit) over spiciness in the balance.</paragraph>
      </stylecomparison>
      <vitalstatistics>
        <OG high="1.095" low="1.070"/>
        <FG high="1.016" low="1.005"/>
        <IBUs high="35" low="22"/>
        <SRM high="6" low="3"/>
        <ABV high="10.5" low="7.5"/>
      </vitalstatistics>
      <commercialexamples>
        <commercial_example>Brigand</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Delirium Tremens</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Dulle Teve</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Duvel</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Judas</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Lucifer</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Piraat</commercial_example>
        <commercial_example>Russian River Damnation</commercial_example>
      </commercialexamples>
      <tags>
        <tag>very-high-strength</tag>
        <tag>pale-color</tag>
        <tag>top-fermented</tag>
        <tag>western-europe</tag>
        <tag>traditional-style</tag>
        <tag>bitter</tag>
      </tags>
    </style>
  </category>
</doc>
