<doc>
  <appendix title="Appendix B: Local Styles">
    <paragraph>*This appendix contains styles submitted by local chapters of the BJCP for styles that are not yet established, but are more important for homebrewers within a single country. They are not included in the main style guidelines, but are available for use by those who wish to use them. The guidelines were written by local members, and were not validated by the BJCP.*</paragraph>
    <locality location="Argentine Styles">
      <style style_id="X1" style_name="Dorada Pampeana">
        <paragraph>*Suggested style placement: Category 18 (Pale American Beer)*</paragraph>
        <paragraph>*En sus comienzos los cerveceros caseros argentinos estaban muy limitados: no existían los extractos, sólo malta pilsen y lúpulo Cascade. Sólo levaduras secas, comúnmente Nottingham, Windsor o Safale. Con estos ingredientes, los cerveceros argentinos desarrollaron una versión específica de la Blond Ale, llamda Dorada Pampeana.*</paragraph>
        <style_section section_name="Impresión general">
          <paragraph>Fácilmente bebible, accesible, con orientación a malta.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Aroma">
          <paragraph>Aroma dulce maltoso ligero a moderado. Es aceptable el aroma frutal bajo a moderado. Debe tener aroma a lúpulo bajo a medio. Sin diacetilo.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Aspecto">
          <paragraph>Color amarillo claro a dorado profundo. Claro a brillante. Espuma baja a medio con buena retención.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Sabor">
          <paragraph>Dulzor maltoso inicial suave. Típicamente ausentes los flavors a caramelo. Flavor a lúpulo ligero a moderado (usualmente Cascade), pero no debería ser agresivo. Amargor bajo a moderado, pero el balance tiende a la malta. Final medio-seco o algo dulce. Sin diacetilo.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Sensación en boca">
          <paragraph>Cuerpo mediano ligero a medio. Carbonatación media a alta. Sensación suave sin amargor áspero o astringencia.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Comentarios">
          <paragraph>Es dificultoso lograr el balance.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Historia">
          <paragraph>Los primeros cerveceros argentinos sólo accedían a malta pilsen y lúpulo cascade y con ellos desarrollaron esta variante de Blond Ale.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Ingredientes">
          <paragraph>Usualmente solo malta pálida o pilsen, aunque puede incluir bajas proporciones de malta caramelizadas. Comúnmente lúpulo Cascade. Levaduras americanas limpias, británicas levemente frutadas o Kölsch, usualmente acondicionada en frío.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <estadísticasvitales>
          <DI high="1.054" low="1.042"/>
          <DF high="1.013" low="1.009"/>
          <IBUs high="22" low="15"/>
          <SRM high="5" low="3"/>
          <GA high="5,5" low="4,3"/>
        </estadísticasvitales>
      </style>
      <style style_id="X1" style_name="Pampas Golden Ale">
        <style_section section_name="Overall Impression">
          <paragraph>Easy drinkability, malt-oriented.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Aroma">
          <paragraph>Light to moderate sweet malty aroma. Low to moderate fruity aroma is acceptable. May have a low to medium hop aroma. No diacetyl.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Appearance">
          <paragraph>Light yellow to deep gold color. Clear to brilliant. Low to medium head with good retention.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Flavor">
          <paragraph>Initial soft malty sweetness. Caramel flavors typically are absent. Mild to moderate hop flavor (usually Cascade), but should not be aggressive. Low to moderate hop bitterness, the balance is normally towards the malt. Half-dry to something sweet finish. No diacetyl.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Mouthfeel">
          <paragraph>Medium-light to medium body. Medium to high carbonation. Smooth without harsh bitterness or astringency.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Comments">
          <paragraph>It is difficult to achieve the balance.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="History">
          <paragraph>At the beginning argentine homebrewers were very limited: there weren´t extract, they could use only pils malt, Cascade hops and dry yeast, commonly Nottingham, Windsor or Safale. With these ingredients, Argentine brewers developed a specific version of Blond Ale, named *Dorada Pampeana*.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Ingredients">
          <paragraph>Usually only pale or pils malt, although may include low rates of caramelized malt. Commonly Cascade hops. Clean American yeast, slightly fruity British or Kölsch, usually packaged in cold.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <vitalstatistics>
          <OG high="1.054" low="1.042"/>
          <FG high="1.013" low="1.009"/>
          <IBU high="22" low="15"/>
          <SRM high="5" low="3"/>
          <ABV high="5.5" low="4.3"/>
        </vitalstatistics>
      </style>
      <style style_id="X2" style_name="IPA Argenta">
        <paragraph>*Suggested style placement: Category 21 (IPA)*</paragraph>
        <paragraph>IPA Especialidad: IPA ARGENTA</paragraph>
        <style_section section_name="Impresión general">
          <paragraph>Una Pale Ale Argentina decididamente amarga y lupulada, refrescante y moderadamente fuerte. La clave del estilo está en la tomabilidad sin asperezas y con un buen balance.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Aroma">
          <paragraph>Intenso aroma a lúpulo con carácter floral y cítrico, derivado de los lúpulos argentinos. Muchas versiones tienen dry-hopping, lo que otorga un carácter a hierba adicional, aunque esto no es requerido. Puede hallarse dulzura límpida a malta e inclusive algo de caramelo, pero con menor tenor que en las Ipas inglesas. Un carácter frutal leve de los ésteres es aceptable, al igual que toques fenólicos producto de la fermentación del trigo, que nunca deben ser dominantes y solo deben agregar complejidad. De todos modos, el carácter relativmente neutro de la fermentación es lo más usual. Puede notarse algo de alcohol en las versiones más fuertes. Sin DMS. El diacetil es un demérito importante en esta cerveza ya que apaga el lúpulo, por lo que nunca debe estar presente.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Aspecto">
          <paragraph>El color varía de dorado medio a cobre rojizo medio. Algunas versiones pueden tener un tinte anaranjado. Debe ser clara, aunque las versiones con dry-hopping o que contienen trigo no malteado pueden tener una leve turbiedad. Buena espuma persistente.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Sabor">
          <paragraph>A lúpulo medio a alto, debiendo reflejar el carácter del lúpulo argentino, con aspectos prominentemente cítricos a pomelo rosado y cáscara de mandarina, que deben dominar. Puede tener también tonos florales como flores de azhar o también herbal y/o resinoso aunque es menos habitual y solo debe agregar complejidad. Amargor medio a medio alto, soportado por una maltosidad limpia que proporciona un balance adecuado.</paragraph>
          <paragraph>Sabor a malta bajo a medio, límpido, aunque son aceptables bajos niveles acaramelados o picantes por el uso de trigo, sea o no malteado. Sin diacetil. Un bajo carácter frutal es aceptable, pero no requerido. El amargor debe permanecer en el retrogusto pero nunca debe ser áspero. Finish medio seco a seco y refrescante. Puede percibirse algún sabor a alcohol en las versiones más fuertes.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Sensación en boca">
          <paragraph>Cuerpo medio liviano a medio, suave, sin astringencias derivadas del lúpulo, aunque la moderada a moderada alta carbonatación puede combinarse con el trigo para dar una sensación seca, aún en presencia de la dulzura de la malta. Suave tibieza a alcohol en las versiones más fuertes (no en todas). Menor cuerpo que la IPA inglesa, y más seca que la IPA Americana.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Historia">
          <paragraph>La versión Argentina del histórico estilo inglés desarrollada en el marco de una serie de encuentros de la Asociación Civil Somos Cerveceros en 2013, donde se fueron definiendo sus características distintivas. Se diferencia de la IPA Americana por agregado de trigo a la receta de granos y el uso de lúpulos Argentinos que tienen características únicas de sabor y aroma. Se busca que las caracterísiticas cítricas del lúpulo Argentino armonicen con el trigo, como sucede en la Witbier. El agregado de bajas cantidades de trigo puede recordar al grist de la Kölsch, donde también hay un frutado producto de la fermentación.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Ingredientes">
          <paragraph>Malta pálida (bien modificada y disponible para maceración simple) y una cantidad de trigo como complemento que no debe superar el 15%; El trigo puede ser malteado o sin maltear. EN el caso de agregar caramelos, deben ser limitados y preferentemente utilizando trigo caramelo. Los lúpulos Argentinos como el Cascade, Mapuche y Nugget son los usuales, aunque puede tener Spalt, Victoria y Bullion para agregar complejidad. Levadura americana que da un perfil límpido o levemente frutal. El agua varía de blanda a moderadamente sulfatada.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <estadísticasvitales>
          <DO high="1065" low="1055"/>
          <DF high="1015" low="1008"/>
          <IBU high="60" low="35"/>
          <SRM high="15" low="6"/>
          <GA high="6.5" low="5.0"/>
        </estadísticasvitales>
        <style_section section_name="Ejemplos comerciales">
          <paragraph/>
          <ejemplo_comercial>Antares Ipa Argenta</ejemplo_comercial>
          <ejemplo_comercial>Kerze Ipa Argenta</ejemplo_comercial>
        </style_section>
      </style>
      <style style_id="X2" style_name="Argentine IPA">
        <style_section section_name="Overall Impression">
          <paragraph>A decidedly hoppy and bitter, refreshing and moderately strong Argentine pale ale. The clue is drinkability without harshness and best balance.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Aroma">
          <paragraph>Intense hop aroma with a citrusy and floral character derived from Argentine hops. Many versions are dry hopped and can have an additional grassy aroma, although this is not required. Some clean malty sweetness and caramel may be found in the background, but should be at a lower level than in English examples. Fruitiness from esters and light phenolics from fermentation of wheat may also be detected in some versions, although a neutral fermentation character is usual. Some alcohol may be noted in stronger versions. No DMS. The diacetyl is a high demerit because it can cover aroma hops, and never should be present.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Appearance">
          <paragraph>Color ranges from medium gold to medium reddish copper; some versions can have an orange-ish tint. Should be clear, although unfiltered dry-hopped versions or with unmalted wheat may be little hazy. Good head stand, persistent.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Flavor">
          <paragraph>Hop flavor is medium to high, and should reflect an Argentine hop character: citrusy, grapefruit and tangerine peel must be dominant. May have some floral character like orange blossoms, or herbal and resinous, although it is less common and should only add complexity. Medium-high to very high hop bitterness, although the malt backbone will support the strong hop character and provide the best balance. Malt flavor should be low to medium, and is generally clean and malty sweet although some caramel or spicy flavors from wheat, malted or unmalted, are acceptable at low levels. No diacetyl. Low fruitiness is acceptable but not required. The bitterness may linger into the aftertaste but should not be harsh. Medium-dry to dry finish, refreshing. Some clean alcohol flavor can be noted in stronger versions.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Mouthfeel">
          <paragraph>Medium-light to medium-bodied mouthfeel without hop-derived astringency, although moderate to medium-high carbonation can combine with wheat to render an overall dry sensation in the presence of malt sweetness. Some smooth alcohol warming can and should be sensed in stronger (but not all) versions. Body is generally less than in English counterparts, and more dry than American counterparts.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="History">
          <paragraph>An Argentine version of the historical English style, developed in 2013 from Somos Cerveceros Association meetings, when its distinctive characteristics were defined. Different from an American IPA in that it is brewed with wheat and using Argentine hops, with its unique flavor and aroma characteristic. Based on a citrus (from Argetine hop) and wheat pairing idea, like in a witbier. Low amounts of wheat are similar to a Kölsh grist, as is some fruitiness from fermentation.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Ingredients">
          <paragraph>Pale ale malt (well-modified and suitable for single-temperature infusion mashing) with up to 15% wheat, either malted or unmalted; Caramel malts should be limited and preferably be caramel wheat. Argentine hops like Cascade, Mapuche and Nugget are typical, although Spalt, Victoria or Bullion may be used to add complexity; American yeast that can give a clean or slightly fruity profile. Water character varies from soft to moderately sulfate.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <vitalstatistics>
          <OG high="1.065" low="1.055"/>
          <FG high="1.015" low="1.008"/>
          <IBU high="60" low="35"/>
          <SRM high="15" low="6"/>
          <ABV high="6.5" low="5.0"/>
        </vitalstatistics>
        <style_section section_name="Commercial Examples">
          <paragraph/>
          <commercial_example>Antares Ipa Argenta</commercial_example>
          <commercial_example>Kerze Ipa Argenta</commercial_example>
        </style_section>
      </style>
    </locality>
    <locality location="Italian Styles">
      <style style_id="X3" style_name="Italian Grape Ale">
        <paragraph>*Suggested style placement: Category 29 (Fruit Beer)*</paragraph>
        <style_section section_name="Overall Impression">
          <paragraph>A sometimes refreshing, sometimes more complex Italian ale characterized by different varieties of grapes.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Aroma">
          <paragraph>Aromatic characteristics of a particular grape have to be noticeable but do should not overpower the other aromas. The grape/wine character should be pleasant and should not have defects such as oxidation. Malt character is usually restrained while hop aroma can range from medium-low to absent. Some examples can have a low to moderately low wild character described as barnyard, earthy, goaty but should not be as intense as in a lambic/fruit lambic. No diacetyl.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Appearance">
          <paragraph>Color can range from gold to dark brown. Reddish/ruby color is usually due to the use of red grape varieties. White to reddish head with generally a medium low retention. Clarity is generally good but can be affected by the use of grape.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Flavor">
          <paragraph>Many interpretations are possible. As with aroma, grape character (must or winey like) must be present but may range from subtle to medium intensity. Varieties of grape can contribute differently on the flavor profile: in general stone/tropical fruit flavors (peach, apricot, pineapple) can come from white grapes and red fruit flavors (e.g., cherry, strawberry) from red grape varieties. Further fruity character of fermentative origin is also common. Different kinds of special malts can be used but should be supportive and balanced, not so prominent as to overshadow the base beer. Roasted and/or strong chocolate character is inappropriate. Some sour notes are common and may help to improve the drinkability but should not be prominent as in Flemish ale/Lambic. Oak flavors, along with some barnyard, earthy, goaty notes, coming from aging in barrels can be present but should not be predominant. Bitterness and hop flavors are generally low. Diacetyl from very low to none.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Mouthfeel">
          <paragraph>Medium-high carbonation improves the perception of aroma. Body is generally from low to medium and some acidity can contribute to increased perception of dryness. Strong examples can show some warming but without being hot or solventy.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="History">
          <paragraph>Produced by many Italian craft breweries during the last years, it represents a communion between beer and wine promoted to the large local availability of different varieties of grapes across the country. They can be an expression of territory, biodiversity and creativity of the brewer. Normally seen as speciality beer in the range of products of the brewery.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <style_section section_name="Ingredients">
          <paragraph>Pils or pale base malt with some adjuncts (if any) or special malts. Grape content can represent up 40% of whole grist. Grape or grape must (sometimes extensively boiled before use) can be used at different stages: boil, primary/secondary fermentation, or aging. Ale or wine yeast can show a neutral character (more common) or a fruity profile (English and Belgian strains). A wide range of hop varieties can be used in low quantities in order not to excessively characterize the beer.</paragraph>
        </style_section>
        <vitalstatistics>
          <OG high="1.090" low="1.043"/>
          <FG high="1.015" low="1.007"/>
          <IBUs high="30" low="10"/>
          <SRM high="30" low="5"/>
          <ABV high="10" low="4.8"/>
        </vitalstatistics>
        <style_section section_name="Commercial Examples">
          <paragraph/>
          <commercial_example>Montegioco Tibir</commercial_example>
          <commercial_example>Montegioco Open Mind</commercial_example>
          <commercial_example>Birranova Moscata</commercial_example>
          <commercial_example>LoverBeer BeerBera</commercial_example>
          <commercial_example>Loverbeer D'uvaBeer</commercial_example>
          <commercial_example>Birra del Borgo Equilibrista</commercial_example>
          <commercial_example>Barley BB10</commercial_example>
          <commercial_example>Barley BBevò</commercial_example>
          <commercial_example>Cudera</commercial_example>
          <commercial_example>Pasturana Filare!</commercial_example>
          <commercial_example>Gedeone PerBacco!</commercial_example>
          <commercial_example>Toccalmatto Jadis</commercial_example>
          <commercial_example>Rocca dei Conti Tarì Giacchè</commercial_example>
        </style_section>
      </style>
    </locality>
  </appendix>
</doc>
